Caleb Henry Carlton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Caleb Henry Carlton Papers 1831-1954 1844-1916
MSS15073
Carlton, Caleb Henry, 1836-1923
2,500 items
5 containers plus 1 oversize
2.5 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States army officer. Correspondence, diaries, articles, military transcripts and papers, biographical and genealogical material, financial records, maps, and charts pertaining to Carlton's service in the Union army and following the Civil War in wars with various Native American groups in the western United States.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Carlton family--Correspondence.; Carlton, Caleb Henry, 1836-1923.; Cook, Henry C.--Correspondence.; Horner, Mabel Carlton, 1872-1961. Mabel Carlton Horner biography of Caleb Henry Carlton.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Correspondence.; Wood, Thomas John, 1823-1906--Correspondence.; Wright, Matthew H.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Libby Prison.
Subjects
Apache Indians.; Atlanta Campaign, 1864.; Beaver Dam Creek, Battle of, Va., 1862.; Cheyenne Indians.; Chickamauga, Battle of, Ga., 1863.; Dakota Indians.; Fortification--Colorado.; Fortification--Nebraska.; Fortification--Wyoming.; Indians of North America--Government relations.; Indians of North America--Wars--1866-1895.; Kennesaw Mountain, Battle of, Ga., 1864.; Malvern Hill, Battle of, Va., 1862.; Military bases--United States.; Peninsular Campaign, Va., 1862.; Ute Indians.
Places
Fort Fetterman (Wyo.); Fort Laramie (Wyo.); Fort Sedgwick (Colo.); Fort Sidney (Neb.); Fort Washakie (Wyo.); Georgia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; Harrison's Landing, Va.--History.; Jonesboro (Ga.)--History.; Marietta (Ga.)--History.; Mechanicsville (Hanover County, Va.)--History.; Richmond (Va.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; West (U.S.)--History.; Yorktown (Va.)--History.
Occupations
Army officers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Caleb Henry Carlton, United States army officer, were given to the Library of Congress by his daughter, Mabel Carlton Horner, and his granddaughter, Elizabeth Carlton Cunningham, in 1962 and 1965.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Caleb Carlton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1836, Sept. 1 Born, Cleveland, Ohio
1859 Graduated, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1862 Married Sadie Pollack
1862 Took part in Peninsular Campaign; promoted to captain
1863 Promoted to colonel, 89th Ohio Infantry
1864 Took part in Atlanta Campaign
1865 Honorably mustered out of voluntary service
1870 Assigned to the 10th Cavalry
1876 Became major, 3rd Cavalry
1889 Promoted to lieutenant colonel, 7th Cavalry
1892 Promoted to colonel, 8th Cavalry
1897 Promoted to brigadier general; retired from army
1923, Mar. 21 Died, Atlantic City, N.J.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Caleb Henry Carlton (1836-1923) span the years 1831-1954, with the bulk of the material from 1844 to 1916. The collection includes notebooks, diaries, family and general correspondence, military papers, financial records, maps and charts, articles by Carlton, and a biography and some letters by his daughter, Mabel Carlton Horner.
The correspondence, diaries, and military papers reveal the life of a cavalry officer in the Civil War and the American Indian wars that followed. During the Civil War, Carlton commanded troops under fire in the Peninsular campaign and at the battles of Yorktown, Mechanicsville, Malvern Hill, and Harrison's Landing. During the Battle of Chickamauga, Carlton and his men were ordered to perform rear-guard action and were captured. After spending five months in Libby Prison, in Richmond, he was exchanged in September 1863. During the Atlanta Campaign, Carlton saw action in the battles of Kennesaw Mountain, Marietta, and Jonesboro. Included in his military papers are documents contemporary to the war as well as recollections of battlefield movements and related matter that he compiled and received after the events.
After the Civil War, Carlton was active in the Plains Wars, including service at Fort Sidney, Nebraska; Camp Auger, Wyoming; Fort Fetterman, Wyoming; Fort Laramie, Wyoming; Fort Washakie, Wyoming; and Fort Sedgwick, Colorado. Diaries and other files document government relations and war with Apache, Cheyenne, Dakota, Ute, and other Native American groups.
Prominent among the correspondents are Generals Thomas John Wood, Henry C. Cook, William T. Sherman, and Matthew H. Wright.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Family correspondence, 1853-1876 (Box 1)
- General correspondence, 1847-1954 (Box 2)
- Military papers (Box 3)
  - Battlefield movements, Chickamauga and Antietam, recollections and related matter, 1888-1906 (Box 3)
  - Orders, 1844-1897 (Box 3)
  - Scholfield affair, 1895-1896 (Box 3)
- Miscellany, 1831-1899 (Box 4)
  - Articles by Carlton (Box 4)
  - Bills and receipts (Box 3)
  - Maps, charts, commissions and awards See Oversize (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, printed matter, and invitations (Box 4)
- Diaries and biographical information (Box 5)
  - Address book (Box 5)
  - Biography of Carlton by Mabel Carlton Horner (daughter) (Box 5)
  - Genealogy of the Carlton family (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous biographical material (Box 5)
  - Notebooks (Box 5)
    - Carlton, Caleb Henry, 1860, 1867, 1876, 1878, 1887, undated (Box 5)
    - Carlton, Sadie Pollock, 1879, 1888, 1890-1894 (Box 5)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Maps, charts, commissions and awards (Container 4) (Box OV 1)